We have a power show today. John
Keryaku. So again, somebody who I always
love talking to, um, John Kyako. He's
former CIA officer, author, and speaker.
His books include the CIA Insiders Guide
to the Iran Crisis: The Reluctant Spy.
And John, you are also on the show with
um Ted Brawl.
Please give me the name of that show.
Uh, it is called uh what's our show
called?
Oh, come on, man.
It's early in the morning for me. I
still have jet lag. Uh, it's uh Yeah,
hold on. I I had it up and I just didn't
write it down when I was um pulling up
information. Hold on. I'll find it for
you. I'll find it. I'll find it.
There were two The other one's Deep
Focus with John Curio. Deep Focus,
right? Yeah. Yeah. And the one with Ted
R is I'm embarrassed. No, it's okay.
It's okay. Like I said, it's early. It's
early. Uh, let's see. This one is
Oh god, what is the name of that show?
Every time I talk to Ted, I'm gonna
search for it, too.
So, it's on YouTube.
Drogram. Drogram. Thank you. Drogram.
Drogram. Every time Ted is on the show,
I always ask him the name of the show.
Um, thank you for joining me, man. I
really appreciate it. I always enjoy
these conversations with you. That's why
I always um I appreciate you that you
come come on. Um let's talk about Iran.
You wrote the book on Iran. Um
I think I told you when you were here
last time I was I thought these talks
were fake at the very least. I've been
saying it for like a month or few
months. Um
there were a few reasons. The escalating
of demands like they I think they broke
down what they wanted once. um they were
always go with demands that were beyond
what Iran obviously was going to accept.
Then there was this kind of context of
events over the course of 20 years where
they've been taking down government
after government after government with
Iran being the last one standing. I do
think Iran thought that the negotiations
were legit. Um, and I think you even
pointed out that even in the newspaper,
Iran was shocked at Whit's openness
because at one point it seemed like they
had a deal. And when Wickoff got back,
oh, they went after him like nobody's
business. Yeah. And the the reason why
there was no deal was because it was the
US that kept changing its demands.
Exactly.
give me your take on all of this, the
12-day war leading up to like if you had
to put this in context in a way that I
guess from a CIA
viewpoint of this because they were
interest in in um they were involved. I
mean uh MSA thanked the CIA as Mark
pointed out at the end of the process
saying hey thanks for all the help and
making this happen. Give me your take on
this just as a general overview and we
can step into it from the overview.
Sure. This is exceedingly complicated.
First of all, um on the one hand, you've
got a president who is beholdened to the
government of Israel. Yes. And
Donald Trump, frankly, will do most of
what Benjamin Netanyahu wants him to do.
We shouldn't be surprised by that.
At the same time, Donald Trump is has
proven to be the kind of guy who
very very much wants a great overarching
deal. Right? So
without having access to the classified
um intelligence,
I'm going to lay out a scenario which I
think is
is
a possibility, maybe even a likelihood.
So
Trump has tried to walk this tight rope
between Israel and the Arabs. Not the
Iranians. I don't think he cares one way
or the other about the Iranians,
but the Arabs. And he has placed his
entire legacy on the line with the
Abraham Accords, which fell apart on
October 7th a couple of years ago.
He wants very much to revive the Abraham
Accords. and being the dealmaker that
everybody says Donald Trump is. What
he's proposing according to Harets,
excuse me, over the weekend
is this overarching deal. Yes, it is
that
um Gaza will fall under the
administration of Saudi Arabia but will
continue to be owned by Israel. The
Saudis will spend maybe as much as a
trillion dollars on a port, an airport,
a water desalination plant, a a sewer
system, and an electrical grid.
There will be no arms permitted in Gaza.
The Saudis would guarantee that. So Gaza
would become its own self-sufficient
economic entity
administered by Saudi Arabia and owned
by Israel with the Saudis running the
day-to-day governance of Gaza
in exchange for that. Wait, wait, John,
can I interrupt one second? There's more
to that also. Depopulation. I mean, they
were talking about kicking. That's
that's been pushed to the side. First of
all, it's it that that's one of the
definitions of genocide.
and the the international community
won't stand for it, including the whole
of Europe.
Donald Trump can't just say, "Look, I'm
going to commit this genocide and I
don't want to hear any any lip about
it." You can't do that.
Why can't he? We've been watching it
take place for over two years or nearly
two years because it's it's one thing to
to call this a war or a fight against
terrorism. It's an it's an entirely
different thing to forcibly lo relocate
an entire people.
I mean, it's quite literally the
definition of genocide. John, I so
disagree with you on this. I'm sorry. I
do.
You can't move two million people. You
can't do it. I know, but they've killed
400 more than 400,000 people. I can show
you the bodies of children starving to
death. I don't disagree with you.
I don't disagree with you, but you can't
the the world won't stand by
as as this becomes a policy by the
United States. A policy by Israel is
different. The fight is on. But for the
United States to say we're either going
to kill, starve, or remove every
remaining Arab in in Gaza, not a chance.
No way. That's what we've been doing.
We've been paying That's not what we've
been doing. Where where have people
look, the Jordanians say not one
Palestinian will enter Jordan. It's
already 50% Palestinian. The Egyptians
closed the border. When Trump floated
the idea of relocating everybody to this
Indonesian island, the Indonesians said,
"Forget it." Then he said, "Albania,
we're going to move them to Albania."
They said, "Not in a million years."
There's no country on earth that is
willing to take the Palestinians. I
guess what I'm getting at, John, is if
we are paying 70% of a genocide,
then
I I'm missing this great distinction
between us paying for it versus us doing
it directly.
Oh, I think there's a there's a massive
distinction.
A massive we're supposed to be the good
guys. We've convinced ourselves that
we're the good guys. and fighting
terrorism, which is sort of the line
that that successive administrations
have used, consider this to be a fight
against terrorism. Forcibly removing 2
million civilians is not fighting
terrorism. It's genocide.
Okay, it it's not even too big anymore.
It's like 1.8. Whatever it is, you can't
do it. And the world won't stand for it.
I mean already Ireland has has
recognized Palestine but this is the
thing. So the Saudis administer Gaza,
the Israelis own it. Um
the Israelis uh will concede that at
some future date Palestine will be uh
recognized as a uh and we've heard that
of course since 1948 will be recognized
as a as an independent country. But then
the Saudis would open an embassy in Tel
Aviv. the Israelis would open an embassy
in Riad and um and all criminal charges
would be dropped against Netanyahu,
which which Trump added at the last
in a truth social post, right?
Yeah. Um
now at the same time
that they they would bring in the
Iranians
uh by allowing the Iranians to to um
to produce enriched uranium up to I
think it was 35%
but that uranium would be
would be housed and this is unacceptable
to the Iranians. Yeah. the uranium would
be housed in uh the UAE. Never accept.
No, they they've already said flat out
not going to happen.
At the same time, you know, the Omanis
said over the weekend that much to their
surprise
um the Iranians are are willing to
continue talks. Now, the US has said
that the talks are going to take place
again on Saturday in Muscat. The
Iranians say that's not true. They've
not agreed to any talks. So, my my guess
is there won't be talks in the near
term. The funerals for the for the
generals, the many generals who were
killed um in this 12-day war took place
on Saturday. And uh I'll tell you, man,
it's rare in any country on earth to see
unity like we saw in Iran on Saturday.
Right there. If Donald Trump thought
that this was going to cause chaos and
bring down the regime, man, he doesn't
know anything about history. You know
what's I spoke to this woman um in Iran
over the weekend and I said why I said
there's a I was like look the US is full
of monsters why would you negotiate with
these monsters I was like if you look at
what took place in Syria Iraq
Afghanistan and she said look we have
our own political realities we have to
deal with and she said there are
political factions that want to
negotiate and it it was required that
they go through the motions in these
negotiations meaning actually have an
honest take at the negot negotiations
just to show the public that you can't
negotiate with the US. Meaning that the
unity that came after the fact was on
some level politically necessary for
them to go through the first negotiation
just to show the public we did this in
honest faith. They lied. And I'll add
too that the Iranians are in a
historically strong position right now.
Um, first of all, I I agree with
Muhammad Mirandi's analysis that that
this bombing campaign by the Israelis
and by the Americans really did almost
nothing to weaken the Iranian
government. U, they they withtood it. It
it unified the country. It brought
everybody together. Generals are very
easily replaced. And it's funny too, not
funny haha, but funny, you know,
interesting that many Iranian generals
have said in
um interviews that they expect to be
killed. You know, they know they're all
targets of the Israelis. And so there's
a very strong pipeline for people to be
promoted to general. You can kill as
many generals as you want. More are
going to pop up. You can't just you
can't cut off the head of the Israeli uh
I'm sorry, of Iranian National Defense.
you just can't do it. Yeah. Um there's
there's also credible information that
the Israelis simply ran out of of
missiles. Yeah. They they gave the the
Iranians their best shot and the
Iranians weathered it. So I think Iran
came out stronger
militarily and politically. In addition,
here in the United States, we
consistently underestimate
the benefit of the JCPOA to Iran.
Whether or not the United States um is
involved or adheres to the JCPOA, I
think is irrelevant because the JCPOA
allowed the whole rest of the world to
trade with Iran. And so you've got the
British, the French, the Germans, the
Japanese, and everybody in between
besides the Russians, the Chinese, and
the Indians all trading with Iran. Here
in the United States, we have a law that
says if you trade with Iran, you are
subject to sanctions, mandatory
sanctions. Mhm. But we've ignored that
law because as soon as we pulled out of
the JCPOA in 2017, Donald Trump told all
of our allies, "Okay, we're out of the
JCPOA, so you have to jump out of the
JCPOA, too, and sanction Iran." And they
said, "Forget it. We're not going to do
that. So, what are you going to do?
You're going to sanction the UK and
France and everybody else in the world."
What the Iranians really really needed
like on an immediate basis was spare
parts for their uh airplanes both
military and civilian and they needed
spare parts for the oil industry and
dredging equipment. And they got it they
got it from the Chinese.
So they don't really need to have
sanctions lifted. it just doesn't matter
anymore because Donald Trump handed them
this situation on a on a silver platter
in 2017 thinking that he was being tough
and strong against the Iranians and
instead he removed any um any
any pressure that the US might have been
able to uh to place against the
Iranians. You know, I'm curious on
something else. Like I I think people,
myself included, was surprised that it's
almost like Iranian internal security.
It's like Swiss cheese where you have a
problem. They have a serious problem
with espionage in their country. Yes.
Why? Why so why is it so well prolific?
I I have to keep reminding myself that
because I'm on the side of the Iranians
in this whole thing, but I have to keep
reminding myself that Iran has big
problems, too. They're perfectly happy
to hang you from a crane by your neck if
you say something that the government
doesn't like. Okay? It's not all milk
and honey over there. Excuse me. They
have serious problems.
And so um
and so this isn't a government that
engenders such good will that it can go
out and do anything it wants. I see.
With that said, then there are people in
the country who hate their government
and are willing to work against it,
risking death. And they already a week
ago, they already started executing
people just suspected of working for the
uh for the Syrians. You know, I I mean
for the Israelis, one of the things that
the Israelis did last week that was just
that was a surprise to me, but was very
effective technique. Something that the
US did to the Iraqis in 2003
is you start calling people and
threatening them. Right? There was a
fantastic
reporting in the Washington Post of a
Mossad a a Farsy speaking Mossad officer
calling a an Iranian general and saying,
"Look, we're going to kill you
tomorrow." Now, we know that they did
this to a number of generals. They first
they they slipped notes under their
apartment doors in the middle of the
night saying, "Hey, we're going to kill
you tomorrow.
This is your only chance. You can come
work for us and we're going to kill you
tomorrow." Then they called their wives
and said, "We're going to kill your
husband tomorrow and we may take down
the entire apartment building. So tell
him to get on the right side of this."
And then finally, they called the
generals themselves, which is what you
heard on that Washington Post um uh
recording, saying, "We're going to kill
you unless you make a video renouncing
support for the Iranian government and
announcing support for the Israeli
government." Not that that's obviously a
death sentence to do something like
that. Why would you do something like
that? But then they legitimately went
out and killed every one of these guys,
more than a half a dozen of them.
So they've got their cell phones, they
have their addresses, they can track
their movements. And one of the things
about the Israelis too, and we saw this
in spades in in Beirut and in southern
Lebanon, is if somebody is in an
apartment building, somebody who's a
target is in an apartment building, they
will take down the entire block
if they can be sure that they're killing
this one person. They'll kill hundreds
just to get that one person.
That's why the death toll was so much
higher. I guess that brings two
questions. For one, why didn't Iran
reciprocate?
And two,
how and let me ask the first the second
one first. How do they go about
recruiting spies? I mean, I would
imagine there would be some Assad agent
who would try to get close to somebody.
Hey, I'll give you money. I give you
because they it ended up having a lot of
Afghans and a lot of Indians and correct
me if I'm wrong on this
they found were working with the
Israelis not to mention you know groups
like MK or whatever right that were
internal yeah this is mostly refugees
this this intelligence network that they
have inside Iran you know the
conventional wisdom Jabarl is that the
Israelis recruit Iranian Jews there are
more Jews in Iran than any other
country. I'm sorry. Yeah, that's right.
There there are more Jews in Iran than
any other country in the Middle East
outside of Israel. Wow. And so the
conventional wisdom is, oh, they just
recruit these Iranian Jews. Not true.
Iranian Jews are loyal to the Iranian
government.
In fact, many of them volunteered
uh for the military just to fight the
Israelis.
But Iran has struggled for decades with
a refugee crisis. Millions, literally
millions of Afghans and Pakistani beluch
have crossed into Iran since 1979.
They're not eligible for Iranian
citizenship. They're not eligible for
Iranian government aid because they're
not Iranians.
And so if you are desperate and hungry
and have no alternative,
that is a vulnerability that the Mossad
has been able to exploit. So if you're
if you're some penniles refugee from
Afghanistan
in Tehran and they give you the Israelis
give you $500 and say, "Get me the
addresses of these five generals or 10
or 20 generals." by God, you're going to
do it and you're going to transmit it
back to them.
How do these refugees get into the
country in general? I mean, this may be
a stupid question.
That's a good question. The border is
absolutely
massive and it's unprotected. It's just
too big and it's too rough and it's too
mountainous. And I'll give you an idea
of this. In 2009, when I joined the
staff of the uh Senate Foreign Relations
Committee, John Kerry, who was the
chairman at the time, told me that he
wanted to reach out to the Iranians.
So, I sent a letter under his signature
to the Iranian ambassador to the United
Nations and I said, "We wanted to meet."
So, I went up to New York and I met with
the Iranian ambassador secretly
and I said, "Senator Kerry is interested
in improving relations with Iran." This
is before the JCPOA was even proposed.
Yeah. Kerry was really gung-ho about
trying to make things right with the
Iranians. And the Iranians said, "That
sounds great. We want weapons. We want
night vision goggles. We want secure
communications with encryption. we want
ammunition. And I was like, "No, no, no,
no, no, no, no. That's not what I'm I'm
not here to talk about that." Right.
Right. Lawyers. It's because they simply
can't control the border. And remember,
this is how all that Afghan heroin gets
into Iran, too. The border is just so
big and so rough and so mountainous,
they just can't control it. Interesting.
Oh, that's so interesting. I guess and
to bounce back to the other question,
why don't they reciprocate? I mean,
Israel had no issue murdering civilians.
They didn't have no issue taking down
apartment buildings. Why does Iran hold
itself to some weird standard when
they're dealing with monsters that don't
have those standards?
That is a very good question. And as as
background, I'm going to say
notice the difference in the death tolls
in the two countries, right? Four, five,
six times the number of people in Iran
were killed than were killed in uh
Israel. Not because the Iron Dome
protected them, but the Iranians
legitimately attacked military and
economic targets. Of course, there were
a couple of errant missiles that that
hit, you know, apartment buildings, but
the Israelis actively
target civilian residential areas.
They want that big death toll. They want
to kill that one general, even if it
means killing 200 other people in the
building. And the Iranians didn't do
that. They they took the high road. And
that was a policy decision they made.
I'm not sure why they did. I think they
did it to be on the right side of
international law. Frankly,
um, one of the things that the Iranians
have have shown the rest of us in two
gorounds now with the Israelis
is that the Iron Dome isn't so vaunted
as it's been cracked up to be. You know,
if those slow motion drones can get
through, and remember in the first go
round, seven drones got through, right?
Seven. That's a lot. That tells me that
that the Iron Dome doesn't really work
like they say it works. And then enough
missiles got through to actually do
damage.
Iran is a gigantic country. It has 92
million people. And just in terms of
area, it's massive. And what does Israel
have? 8 million, I guess. Yeah. Yeah. So
Iran can, you know, take a licking and
keep on ticking as the old Timex
commercial used to used to say.
Oh, your point is Oh, I'm sorry. I
thought you were still going. Your your
point is effectively they willingly
absorb knowing for Yeah. I guess this is
the argument I used to make too that if
it's pound-for-pound, even if Israel
condition out three times more, Israel
is going to get crushed again. Going to
get crushed. The Israelis, the Israelis
would have to use nuclear weapons. And
to do that would be I think it would be
the end of Israel. Why do you think it
would be the end of Israel? Because the
West with the United States aside,
because we're, you know, beholden to the
Israelis, I think the West would walk
away from Israel if they use nuclear
weapons
without having nuclear weapons used on
them. But now, but see, this is the part
that that gets me, and I guess this is
where my main disagreement goes with
this.
Intellectually, I would hope that to be
true, but by the same token, I never
thought I'd watch a genocide take place
in real time. Like, meaning I never
thought I'd watch kids walking around
like skeletons. That is mind-blowing.
I've never seen that. Nor did I think I
would ever see that. Have you ever been
like to the West Bank or Gaza? Yeah,
Bethlehem.
That's a Christian That's a Christian
town. Have you been like to Nablus,
let's say, or No, Jamar, it is
it's like walking from the from the
first world into the into the fourth
world. It's the biggest prison on earth,
the biggest open air prison on earth.
You know,
my mom said to me one time in 2008, my
dad had died and she wanted to travel.
So, she called me one day and she said,
"I think I'm going to go to Ireland with
your sister." And I said,"Ireland?" I
said, 'What do you want to go to Ireland
for in February? You know how cold and
rainy it is in Ireland. I said, 'The
priest at my church is taking a group to
Israel, Mom. You should go to Israel.
And she's like, "Oh, that's a great
idea." So, she and my sister went. My
mom had zero political perspective.
Didn't know anything.
Wasn't really interested in politics or
foreign affairs. She came back
as a 100% Palestine activist. She said
to me, she was so sweet about it. She
said, "Did you have any idea how those
Israelis treat the Palestinians?"
And I said, "Of course, like my whole
adult life I've been watching the way
they treat the Palestinians." And she
said she cried a couple of times. She
cried at a roadblock one time. They had
a Palestinian Christian Greek Orthodox
driver for their little, you know, their
little van that that held 12 people. Oh,
this happened to me, too. Go ahead,
please. And she said the guy was a
professional driver and he would drive
them to Bethlehem and drive them to
Nazareth and just sit in the van. So
they come to an IDF roadblock and the
guy's reading some some pulp fiction,
you know, novel while everybody's inside
the church taking pictures and an IDF
soldier grabbed the book out of his hand
and opened it up and said, "No picture
of Arafat on this page." And tore out
the page and threw it at him. No picture
of Arafat on this page. And he tore
clumps of pages out and threw it at him.
And the poor driver just sat there and
took it. Yeah. And she said to him, "Why
do you allow them to treat you like
that?" And he said, "Madam, the
alternative is that they shoot me."
Yeah. And then she said, as if that
wasn't bad enough, as they're entering
the West Bank, there are these 30foot
walls with barbed wire on the side
um or on the top rather that the
Israelis said were to keep the
Palestinians out of Israel. And she
said, "They're not. They're to keep the
Palestinians or sorry, to keep the
Palestinians in Palestine in cages. It's
a prison." And I said calimera, it's
something the Greeks say. Good morning.
Like you just woke up and realized that
this is the reality in in Palestine or
occupied Palestine, which is what the
West Bank is. So I think part of our
problem here in the United States is
most Americans either don't know that or
refuse to acknowledge it. You know, I
taught years ago at Liberty University,
an evangelical university. I'm not
evangelical. I have nothing in common
with them, but they offered me a
teaching position and I accepted it. And
for whatever reason, I'm still on the
list serve of professors. And I mean, I
taught there in 2011.
Yeah. Um 200 2011. So I'm still on the
list serve. And the the the ugly
viciferous
hatred that I see for Palestinians on
this list serve is disguised as
support for Israel and opposition to
terrorism.
Well, none of these people have ever met
a Palestinian. None of these people have
ever been to Palestine or to Israel.
They're just going by what they see on
Fox and the One America Network and what
they hear, you know, in their Bible
beating uh evangelical churches.
So, a lot of this is a result in the
United States as a result of ignorance,
in many cases, willful ignorance. And I
think that as things continue to get
worse
and our European allies become more
vocal in their opposition to what we're
seeing today, starving, literally
starving children, I think they're going
to begin to drag Americans with them in
that direction.
Mark, I I mean, I'm sorry, not Mark. Um,
John, I I don't I I got to be honest. I
don't see it. I You know, stuff like
this is just every day. No,
that's just daily. Just children as
skeletons. Yes. And you see like when I
was in Bethlehem, it was never that bad.
Like Oh, no. Ever. I remember they
pulled my van driver out because
apparently he didn't have some kind of
identification. Took the man to jail
somewhere. And in perfect English, hey,
um, another driver will come in a moment
to take you to wherever you're going.
And you know it's like you see that
stuff like you when I remember when we
got into LA looks like little America
and then when you cross into Bethlehem
you're in like Yeah. It just too
different. Different different country.
Yes. It is bizarre. Yes. And you know
you get back to the States. My ex-wife I
remember the first time she went to
Israel with me and she didn't understand
why I was being a bit of a dick. Right.
Because for one I didn't want to be
there at that point. What was this?
This was maybe four or five years ago.
Recently. This was recent. She didn't
She didn't get it cuz she's not really
political in that sense. And I remember
when we were leaving, she says, "You
know, I was at the museum." She says,
"It dawned on me if Israel, if all of
these Israelis came here, who was here
for, you know, when they got here?" And
she's like, it kind of dawned on her
like, "Oh, that's why all of these
people are in um van in these places
with guns. That's why they were running
around with all of the military. That's
why meaning it took her a while to click
of who was here before these people got
here.
It it is it's just it is a wild it is an
alternate reality. It is bizarre." And
Americans have no idea. The last time I
was there, I was in Jerusalem. This is
2022. I was actually there to cover the
Israeli elections for Sputnik. Yeah. And
I remember this. I remember them sending
you I'm sorry. I remember sending you.
There were two things. One, I I would
see these signs everywhere, billboards,
banners. We are with you, America. I'm
like, on what? You're with us on what?
We don't want to be with you. Like, what
are these stupid billboards? That was
the first thing. The second thing,
it was my last full day in Israel and I
had to do actually I had to do your
show. Um, you were early in the morning.
Was it 7 to 10, I think, uh, Eastern.
Okay. So, so Israel was seven uh, seven
hours ahead and I was going to be on at
8. So, I had the day free until 3:00
p.m. until I had to get on your show.
And I hadn't yet gone to the Mount of
Olives and I wanted to see the Garden of
Gethsemane and the Virgin Mary's uh you
know, tomb and stuff like that. So, I
went in the morning and I I went to the
Mount of Olives and then I thought,
"Okay, I I'm going to go back into the
old city of Jerusalem and buy a
souvenir." So, I'm on the Mount of
Olives. You go down into the valley and
then back up to get to the old city. And
to tell you the truth, I was 115 pounds
heavier at the time. And it was faking
hot that day. So when I get back up to
the old city, I'm winded.
So I sat on a bench
like 20 feet outside the iron gate,
which is one of the gates of the old
city. Mhm. And there's a woman sitting
there and she says, "Hi." And I said,
'Hi.' And she asked me where I was from.
And I said, 'D, where are you from? Oh,
I'm from Brooklyn. Isn't this city
amazing? Yeah, it's amazing, but I can't
believe how they treat the Palestinians,
etc. So, we're just sitting there
chatting
and as I'm talking to her, I'm watching
again from 20 feet away. I'm watching
the actual entrance to the uh I'm the
the iron gate, which isn't iron. It's
stone. But anyway, um there were three
IDF soldiers standing in the iron gate
and they're just standing there milling
around and it's this hustle and bustle
of Palestinians
holding, you know, crates of fruits and
vegetables, dates, and they're they're
going about their day trading, buying,
selling. There's this one Palestinian
guy who's kind of milling around.
One of the IDF soldiers went over and he
was about 10 ft away. Went over to ask
him, "What are you doing?" And as the
soldier went over there,
he pulls out a knife and he stabs the
guy twice. He stabs the soldier twice in
the stomach, right underneath the the
bulletproof vest that he was wearing.
Immediately, one of the other soldiers
put up his gun and shot him and killed
him right there in front of my eyes.
This woman I'm with screams and I said,
"We better get the hell out of here cuz
they're going to lock it down." I took
off. I was directly across the sidewalk,
the walkway from the back entrance to
the um the um the Rockefeller
Archaeological Museum. So I ran that
way, came out on the other side, went to
my hotel and called Sputnik, and she ran
the other way back to the Mount of
Olives. They locked down the entire old
city of Jerusalem.
And if I hadn't been able to run like
that, I would have been caught up in all
that hell.
I mean, within minutes,
helicopters flying around, everything's
locked down, armored personnel carriers
entering the old city. It was, it was
awful. And then I put on the Israeli
news, the English language Israeli news,
just to see what they were saying about
this. And it was, "They hate us more
than they love life itself. It is only
by the grace of God that our man wasn't
killed. You can see that they have only
murder in their hearts. It's like, are
you [__] kidding me?
It's like they don't see it. They just
don't see it. It's the most bizarre
thing. I remember I was having a
conversation. I was interviewing um I
guess it was a debate with Benjamin
Netanyahu's press guy once and to me the
most rational thing in the world is do
you understand that because of the way
you treat them you're creating your
monsters they don't get it completely
over completely over it's you know I I
gave a I gave a talk to um to the
Canadian Foreign Ministry on Thursday
last week big big thing I had 125 people
show up for the Zoom Zoom call and um
one of the very first questions they
asked me was how do we get out of this
this constant cycle of terrorism and
war? And I said, you know, this was one
of the very first lessons that I learned
when I was the the head of
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
for the CIA.
I said, we started capturing al-Qaeda
fighters immediately as soon as I
arrived. we would just bust down the
door and grab these guys. And the shock
for me was that to a man, they were all
children, 18, 19, 20 years old, and they
all told exactly the same story. They
were from isolated villages in their
home countries all across the Middle
East. They couldn't read or write. They
had no job skills.
They wanted to get married, but no man
would let his daughter marry some kid
who can't read, can't write, and doesn't
know how to do a job. So, the local imam
said, "Why do you want to stay in this
village? You should go to Afghanistan
and make jihad against the Americans,
and we'll give you $300 a month, and if
you're martyed, we'll give your parents
a $500 martyrdom bonus." Wow. And I
said, "These guys couldn't find the
United States on a map. They had no idea
what US policy was. There was no
inherent or intrinsic hatred of the
United States. It's that they were poor
and they had no hope." So I said, "If
you want to know how to get out of this
cycle of violence and terrorism,
education and economic development."
Yeah. And I would tell the Israelis
exactly the same thing. You can't kill
everybody. You may think you can, but
you can't. And the only way to get out
of this is you have to give people a
reason to want to lay down their arms.
You have to allow them
self-determination.
You have to allow them to develop their
economy. You have to allow them to raise
happy families. Give them something to
live for.
You can't just occupy their land, steal
their homes, starve their children,
shoot their fathers, blow up their
hospitals. That's not tenable.
But the Israelis don't want to hear
that. No, they don't.
John,
always appreciate you, man. My pleasure.
It's good to see you again. One last
thing. What do you think happens from
here?
I think they they've never accepted a
ceasefire. Um Yeah. And they but oddly
enough and and I guess there are two
parts to this. One, they've never
accepted a ceasefire meeting. They're
bombing Lebanon today. They've been
killing people left and right. That's
right. Um you know, and that's another
thing that hasn't quite made the
American media. They're bombing the hell
out of Lebanon the last couple of days.
Nobody's paying any attention.
It's an untenable situation. You know,
it's funny. We talk a lot about the 67
war, the 73 war. We don't talk so much
about the 82 war where the Israelis got
their asses kicked in Lebanon and had to
withdraw. We we don't talk about the
first and second inifatas where the
Israelis got their asses kicked again.
And so, you know, they're going to have
to they're going to have to come up with
some sort of proposal or maybe have a
proposal imposed on them because you and
I, Jamar, are not the only ones watching
this news footage of starving children.
We're not talking about Yemen here or
Somalia. We're talking about Israel, a
first world country, and they are
consciously and purposefully
starving children to death. It's
untenable.
John Kuryaku. John Kuryaku. He is there
we are. Former CIA um officer, author,
speaker. Um books include the CIA
Insiders Guide to the Iran Crisis, The
Reluctant Spy. Also, you can find John
on two shows. Please give us those two
shows, John. Uh Drogram, that's along
with Ted Raw. And the other is called
Deep Focus with John Kuryaku. Deep
Focus. John, thank you for this, man. I
really appreciate it. Thank you, buddy.
Good to see you. Be safe. Okay. Have a
good one.
All right.